<chapter version="5.0" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  
  <title>Template document overview</title>
 
    <para>The OpenPOWER Foundation documentation template provides a framework for OpenPOWER public and private
          documentation.  The goal of the template and this writeup is to promote community contributions
          to OpenPOWER documenation and to enable new contributions within a common look and feel. </para>

    <para>The major sections of this document addresses the following topics:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Getting started: This section details tools and commands used to contribute to OpenPOWER documentation.
              All users who are new to OpenPOWER Foundation documentation should start here.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Creating a new document: This section provides step-by-step instructions on how to create a new document 
              from scratch.  Use this section to start a new documentation project.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Modifying an existing document: This section highlights common steps in editing an existing OpenPOWER
              Foundation document.  Use this section as a guideline for contributing to an existing document.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Debugging build failures: This section provides examples of the two most common types of build failures
              and helps users find the relevant failure information.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Policies and conventions: This secion contains
              the generally accepted guidelines for creating OpenPOWER documentation.  Use this section as a reference
              for documentation style beyond template provided features.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Frequently asked questions: This section answers common questions.  Use this section when the other sections
              do not answer your questions.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Where to find more information: This section provides pointers to on-line information about XML, Docbook,
              Maven, and other relevant references.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>In addition to OpenPOWER Foundation specific topics, <xref linkend="section_template_examples"/> 
          provides examples of common documenation constructs in XML.</para>

  <xi:include href="sec_template_getting_started.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="sec_template_new_document.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="sec_template_existing_document.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="sec_template_debugging.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="sec_template_policies.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="sec_template_faq.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="sec_template_references.xml"/>


</chapter>
